<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="translation"><body><pb facs="#f0003"/><div facs="#f0003"><p>Having previously put forward a book of architecture, which contains both the plans of fifty different buildings, with ample statement not only of the commodities but also of the eye-catching of each of them, by which we know to what extent they can come back to one another, it seemed to me very reasonable and almost necessary for the accomplishment of the preceding work, to make another volume of some beautiful inventions and various ordinances to enrich both the inside and the outside of each building. Which volume I have divided into seven parts according to the diversity of things we want to enrich.

In the first part are drawn twenty orders of fireplaces all different, some of which are light and low price, the other rich and sumptuous, and others in a medium way. Others are open, both on the front as well as on the dextral and sinister sides to serve in large rooms, which is necessary that in several places the heat of the fire can be communicated, and the others are opened only by the front, to use it in rooms, wardrobes and medium rooms. This notwithstanding, each one at his pleasure will be able to accommodate both of them in any place he likes, and even apply to it no rich stones, either of jasper, marble or others, with such currencies as he thinks fit, as the drawings clearly demonstrate. But among all of them will find a garnished cross in the middle of his face, which seems very new and strange thing, and yet easy enough to understand and implement, as we can know by the drawing that I added after his order, which are represented two solid triangles, one above and one below the cross, so that the smoke, being thereby constrained by the bottom, to separate into two pipes joining to the dexter and sinister of the crossed, can rise above this and withdraw in the same conduit.

In the second part are twelve ways of skylights, none with pilasters and others in projections of column or terms, between which there is a projection more before the others, like approximately of two feet, or foot and a half, in order to satisfy those who wish to project beyond the body of the wall. Similarly, there are some very rich orders, which will be situated in the middle of many, when it happens that on the same face of the house there are three, or five, or seven, and we want to make one of the middle more apparent in wealth than the others.

The third part contains fourteen doors of various order, of which the six are traced in large drawing, and the eight others in smaller.

The fourth part is six fountains, with the shortened plan of each of them, drawn on the first page, by which you will easily hear the tower, the middle and the plate of the fountain.

The fifth part is six wells, each with its shortened plan, similarly to the first sheet, which can, as in the previous, enough to know the turn, build and trim of the well.

The sixth part is of six pavilions (I mean pavilions that are commonly erected in the middle of a garden, either of wood, or of stone) from which one can know the plate and the convenience by the plan of a dene each one to the first leaflet, as in front. Between these pavilions, the first two figured on the second sheet each contain five pavilions, namely four little ones with four entrances, and a large one in the middle separated from them by means of the alleys, as apparent by their said plans.

The seventh and last part is ten burials, eight of which are in small figure, and two in larger. In this part, as well as in the first three of this volume, I have not added any plan, because the drawings and figures make it sufficiently clear what should be the arrangement of the work.</p></div></body></text>