<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="translation"><body><pb facs="#f0002"/><div facs="#f0002"><p>TO THE KING.
Sire, considering that your ancestors have always had in singular recommendation the intelligence and advancement of all liberal sciences, and even of the art of Architecture, as it appears both by the knowledge of the good letters now flourishing throughout your Kingdom, that by the excellent and sumptuous Architecture of the buildings they edified, I have ascertained that your noble blood and royal food will not only retain this virtuous and laudable custom of your very illustrious progenitors, but will also add to it some particular ornament and growth. By what, SIRE, although of this small talent that it pleased God to put in my hands, all my life I strove to illustrate this art of Architecture, as testify several and various books by me often brought to light if ever since your advent to the kingdom to which God has seated you, I have endeavored to employ myself better than ever to undertake things rarer and more excellent, which may bring to your Royal mind some recreation and pleasure. And for that, SIRE, that of this affection and will of mine I have always desired to make some proof to you, having lately completed this work of several inventions greatly useful and necessary to adorn and embellish all kinds of buildings, I have dare to present it to your Majesty, for the first pledge of obedience and humble service which it owes you and wishes to do, entreating you very humbly, Sire, that you please receive it benignly from your very affectionate servant and subject, waiting may God grant me the grace to present to you another, as I have been permitted and ordained by your predecessors Kings, so many singular drawings and works of your city of Paris as of your palaces and royal buildings, with some most sumptuous among the other peculiarities of your noble kingdom, in the reign of which God gives us the grace to see you, Sire, in all happiness very long prosper to the praise of his name and contentment with your subjects, by which will be your name dedicated to immortality.</p></div></body></text>