<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="translation"><body><pb facs="#f0002"/><div facs="#f0002"><p>Hierosme De Gourmont, To All Workers, Goldsmiths, Tailors, Engravers, Painters, Embroiderers, Upholsterers, &amp; other men of good spirit, studious, of true antiquity, &amp; perfect design. Every day here laboring, &amp; still working (my friends) to represent to you in paper or by charter, from which I have little to gain, the true and perfect patterns, from antique as well as modern Italy, France, Germany, &amp; lands of the Middle East: I do not say what belongs to architecture, which must be designed with reason, and extracted from the best authors, both Greek and Latin and vulgar. But I enter as [does] the engraver who touches sculpture and design for the goldsmith metalworkers, apportioning and extracting from antique [designs], however constructing and organizing more for happiness of the eye by those who know to provide instruction: wanting in said place to also satisfy you well as I believe I have done and do, from day to day for all true enthusiasts of these artistic techniques and even of the description of the world: in which with the aid &amp; favor of the Very Christian &amp; Magnanimous King Francis, first of this name. We have given some light though the provision of these specific patterns, which I have taken from ones very freshly brought from the countries of Italy, &amp; Germany and exhibited for sale in this city of Paris. Now to give you the greatest opportunity for contentment, here is a book of Moorish designs which is presented as an offering to you but understand that everything thus as they [the designs] are as simple and true as it is possible to have them portrayed also [the plates] have been cut by an highly skilled understanding of this art. Review the gift as soon as it is presented to you and you will find that there will be nothing that can be offered for embellishment that cannot have an example in it. With the knowledge you have, take my effort to brighten your work so that it will prove more agreeable to others, notable, enriching the fabric, and impressive. In Paris on the first day of May, one thousand five hundred and forty six.</p></div></body></text>